<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The harmonie of the lawe and the gospel Wherin is plainly shewed, that howsoeuer they differ in time and some other circumstances, yet in substance they are one &amp; the same. And by waie of application, the pretended antiquitie of Poperie is discouered, and found to be a meere nouelty: deliuered in a sermon at Pauls-crosse, the 9. of Aug. 1607. by George Cresvvell, minister of Gods word.</title>
            <author>Creswell, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117450</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852663</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852663</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12273)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1233:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The harmonie of the lawe and the gospel Wherin is plainly shewed, that howsoeuer they differ in time and some other circumstances, yet in substance they are one &amp; the same. And by waie of application, the pretended antiquitie of Poperie is discouered, and found to be a meere nouelty: deliuered in a sermon at Pauls-crosse, the 9. of Aug. 1607. by George Cresvvell, minister of Gods word.</title>
                  <author>Creswell, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 54, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By H. L[ownes] for William Leake,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 6038a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177845:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177845:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177845:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177845:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HARMONIE OF the LAWE and the GOSPEL.</p>
            <p>Wherin is plainly ſhewed, <hi>that howſoeuer they differ in time</hi> and ſome other circumſtances, <hi>yet in ſubſtance they are</hi> one &amp; the ſame.</p>
            <p>And <hi>By waie of application, the pretended</hi> anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of Poperie is diſcouered, and <hi>found to be a meere nouelty:</hi> Deliuered in a Sermon at <hi>Pauls-</hi>croſſe, the 9. of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1607. <hi>by</hi> GEORGE CRESVVELL, <hi>Miniſter of Gods word.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>H. L.</hi> for WILLIAM LEAKE.</p>
            <p>1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177845:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177845:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Sir</hi> Thomas Weſt, Knight, Lord <hi>Lawarre,</hi> all <hi>peace, proſperitie, and happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, hauing at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Knight (an Alderman of the Cittie of <hi>London)</hi> gathered this my Sermon into writing, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered him the Copie; I was ſoone after deſired (nay, importuned) by
<pb facs="tcp:177845:4"/> others (my worſhipful good friends) to giue conſent for the printing of it. Which, when I could not, in good manners (as I thought) farther put off; I was at length induced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend vnto: the rather, both in regard of the benefit, which by this my weake meanes may growe to the Church of God: as alſo, that (by ſeeking ſhelter vnder your Ho: protection) I had now a fitte op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie (long wiſht-for) to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt my dutifull reſpect, and humble affection to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. This your Patronage, if it pleaſe your Honour (as an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your former fauours) gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly to vouchſafe mee; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but alſo acknowledge my ſelfe herein the more obliged in
<pb facs="tcp:177845:4"/> al bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duties. Thus, humbly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your Lordſhips fauourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of my faithful endeauours, I take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, euer in all duty: <hi>GEO. CRESWELL.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>Dated the 8. of <hi>October.</hi> 1607.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177845:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177845:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Galati. 3. verſ. 17. 18. 19. 20.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p n="17">17. <hi>And this I ſay; that the Law, which was</hi> 400. <hi>and</hi> 30. <hi>yeares after, cannot diſannull the couenant that was confirmed afore of God, in reſpect of Chriſt, that it ſhould make the promiſe of none effect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="18">18. <hi>For, if the inheritance be of the Law, it is no more by promiſe: but God gaue it vnto</hi> Abraham <hi>by promiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="19">19. <hi>Wherefore then ſerueth the Lawe? It was added becauſe of the tranſgreſſions, till the Seede came vnto the which the promiſe was made: and it was ordained by Angels in the hand of a Mediator.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="20">20. <hi>Now, a Mediatour, is not a Mediatour of one: but God is one.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle (right honourable, right worſhipfull, and welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Chriſtians) in all this whole Epiſtle, doth grauely, and ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confute them that in his time mingled the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177845:6"/> Lawe with the Goſpell, and (as if that Chriſt had beene inſufficient for vs) did teach that Circumciſion and the obſeruation of the Lawe was neceſſarie for the Gentiles, that had alreadie beleeued in Chriſt. Further, he demonſtrateth, that the Lawe did ſubdue al men to the curſe, and therefore they did ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnwiſely, that hoped for any bleſſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lawe. Yea, God would haue it to bee ſo, that all men might knowe that they ſhould be bleſſed and ſaued in Ieſus Chriſt: in whom God had promiſed the ſame vnto <hi>Abraham.</hi> Now, when hee had confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this by the teſtimonies of the ſcripture; hee vſeth a ſimilitude, or example of teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or wills: wherein he teacheth vs, that they were too raſh that thought it lawfull for them to doe that in the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, which is vnlawful to bee done in the will of a man being once well confirmed &amp; ſealed; a matter worthie of our beſt conſideration: becauſe God was willing to comprehend the whole manner of our ſaluation, vnder the word or forme of a Will, or couenant: &amp; ſuch a one, as could no otherwiſe be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or ratified, but by the enſuing death of his onely begotten ſonne; which was an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Gods goodnes, and mercie, full
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177845:6"/> of moſt ſweet and excellent comfort. God was willing that his onely begotten ſonne (obedient to his decree, by whom hee made and gouerneth all things) ſhould be made man, and deliuered him vp to the bitter and ignominious death of the Croſſe, that hee might adopt vs into his children, and make vs fellow inheriters of his kingdome: Euen vs (I ſay) who, how honorable, rich or great ſoeuer wee bee, yet are we of our ſelues ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the ſonnes of wrath. Therefore, it is manifeſt that our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth proceed and come vnto vs from the free mercie of God, without any deſert of ours: And, as this ſcripture doth maintaine the certaintie of it, ſo doth it admoniſh vs of our dutie: which is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with Chriſt only, &amp; remember that we owe our ſelues &amp; al that we haue vnto God, who hath aduanced vs miſerable wretches vnto the dignitie of his ſons. Thus much be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as an Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the Text. Now, let vs proceed in the words of the Apoſtle: who doth more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply declare that which before he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning the couenant of God, in theſe words; <hi>And this I ſay, that the Lawe which was</hi> 403. <hi>yeares after, &amp;c.</hi> The ſumme of this is, that the Couenant of God, was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177845:7"/> ſo firme and ſure, that it could not bee abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by the Lawe. So that the Apoſtles words are as much as if he ſhould haue ſaid; It may be, I may ſeeme vnto many to ſpeake obſcurely; yet I wil ſpeake truth, as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is: for as God (touching his eſſence) is eternall, and is not changed, ſo alſo his wil is conſtant in it ſelfe, and his decrees are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable. For, as ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſaie, When the Lord of Hostes hath determined any</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 14. 27</note> 
               <hi>thing, who ſhall diſannull it?</hi> Wherfore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God gaue a lawe afterwards to our forefathers: yet notwithſtanding, this law, which followed, 400 and 30 yeares after, was not able to aboliſh or any way to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt that ancient couenant that God before had made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and confirmed it by authoritie.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle, heere, draweth an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from time: in the which (that wee may note this by the way) appeareth with what diligence the Apoſtles read &amp; ſearched the ſcriptures. Many other ſuch like places we haue in the word of God. <hi>Steuen</hi> the proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martyr, in his Apologie in the ſeauenth of <note place="margin">Acts. 7</note> the Acts, from the ſucceſſion of time, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a reaſon, wherby hee proues, that what excellent thing ſoeuer our fathers had, it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177845:7"/> came vnto them from the free mercie of God. Our Apoſtle doth the like in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <note place="margin">Act. 13.</note> ſermon that hee made vnto the Iewes at <hi>Antioch,</hi> a Citie of <hi>Piſidia:</hi> And in his Epiſtle to the Romans, doth teach vs, from <note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> the circumſtance of time, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was Iuſtified by faith onely, and not by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion; it being no other but a ſeal of that righteouſnes hee had already obtained by faith. In all which is propoſed a notable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for miniſters, to imitate this dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Apoſtles: remembring that the holy ſcriptures were not written by the priuate will, or motion of man; but the whole ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as ſaid the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> by <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 20. 21. 2. Tim. 3. 16.</note> the inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, who doth nothing raſhly, but all things with diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and iudgement. For, there is nothing ſo ſmall in the ſcriptures, but is verie much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable to our inſtruction and comfort, if it be diligently conſidered. And the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are the ineſtimable riches of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: to the deſtroying and confounding wherof, no induſtrie and endeuour of man is of it ſelfe ſufficient. But, arguments that are taken from the circumſtance of time, are firme and ſure, when men doe ſpeak of God and of the action of eternall ſaluation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177845:8"/> God is ſubiect to no alteration, or change of times. For, as ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, One day with the Lord, is as a thouſand</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>yeares: and a thouſand yeares as one day.</hi> And Ieſus Chriſt, (who is conſtituted &amp; made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs of God the Father, the author &amp; Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of ſaluation) is yeſterday, and to day, and <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 8.</note> the ſame for euer: He is the Lambe of God who was offered from the beginning of the World, becauſe that in his merite the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <note place="margin">Apoc. 13, 8</note> fathers, who (from <hi>Adam)</hi> beleeued his comming, were ſaued: and by him alſo ſhal be ſaued to the ende of the world, all that doe apprehend him with a true and liuely faith.</p>
            <p>That this ſhould bee thus effected, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie. For, if wee were iuſtified and ſaued by any other meanes then our auntient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were; there would follow a double manner of Iuſtification, and a diuerſe, or double meane of ſaluation: which cannot be; becauſe Chriſt hath ſaide, that hee is the <note place="margin">Iohn. 10. 9.</note> doore by whom we muſt enter into the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of his ſheep-fold; that is of his Church and Saluation: calling all them theeues, and robbers, that endeuour to clyme vp by any other meanes. To whom the Apoſtles <note place="margin">Acts. 4. 12.</note> conſent, ſeeing they affirme no other name
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177845:8"/> to be giuen vnto men vnder heauen, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee muſt bee ſaued, but onely the name of Ieſus. This may be confirmed by diuers reaſons in the word of God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the elect, that are heires of ſaluation, in the ſcriptures are called the children of <hi>Abraham;</hi> Now, how can they be ſo called, if they ſhould be iuſtified and ſaued by any other meanes then <hi>Abraham</hi> was? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, all thoſe things that God in times paſt hath determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, concerning the monarchies and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this worlde, remaine firme and certain: for they did ariſe &amp; fall in that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and time, that <hi>Daniel</hi> &amp; other Prophets foreſhewed they ſhould ariſe and come to their end. And ſhall we then think, that God would be ſo vnmindefull of himſelfe, that hee would ſet vp and pull down the Lawes of his kingdome, or in thoſe Lawes (for mens ſakes) would alter and change any one of thoſe things, that by his eternall decree, he had determined before we were <hi>in natura reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> yea before the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the world were laied. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, if the Law (then the which the whole world neuer ſawe a thing more magnificent, whether wee haue a reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect vnto the giuing of it, full of maieſtie &amp; feare; or the forme of the outward worſhip; or the example of holy men, that liued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177845:9"/> the diſcipline of the Lawe) was not able to abrogate the Couenant of eternall ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which God (in times paſt) had made with <hi>Abraham:</hi> then what fooliſhneſſe, yea rather madneſſe ſhall it bee, that in changing of this couenant, wee ſhould attribute any thing to humane traditions, which God will not entertaine in his worſhip; as being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned by authoritie both of the olde and newe Teſtament. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, and laſtly, if God himſelfe were vnwilling to giue vnto vs a Lawe, which ſhould aboliſh the auncient promiſe and couenant of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham:</hi> ſhall wee then grant this to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and fooliſh men, that they ſhould ſet downe newe meanes to attaine vnto ſaluation, whereby Iuſtification by faith (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the authority of the new Teſtament) ſhould bee aboliſhed, or any way corrupted?</p>
            <p>Then hereby are they confuted, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Poperie by Antiquitie; but doe accuſe the Goſpell, and faith (that is grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the onely merite of Chriſt) of noueltie. Beloued, if wee conſider the whole matter, wee ſhal then ſee, that there are fewe things in Poperie, that deſerue the name of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: becauſe it may be ſhewed out of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177845:9"/> hiſtories, both at what time, and by what men the moſt part of all thoſe things that by papiſtes are eſteemed, had their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. Firſt, to beginne with their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie: It is manifeſt it was in the yeare of Chriſt, ſixe hundred &amp; ſeauen, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts. The Apoſtles being mindefull of the admonition of Chriſt, neuer thought of any ſuch matter, neither amongſt their ſucceſſors was there any contention about the ſupremacie, vntill the dayes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Mauritius,</hi> when <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Popiſh ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> an ambitious man, calling a ſynode, determined that the Supremacie ought to belong to the Church of <hi>Constantinople;</hi> that like as all the Chriſtian worlde was ſubiect to the Emperour of that place: ſo in like ſort all Churches ought to acknowledge the Patriarke of that Citie, for the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall paſtour and chiefe Prieſt. This was in the yeare of Chriſt fiue hundred foureſcore and fiue. Againſt the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this man, <hi>Pelagius</hi> the ſecond, being then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> oppoſed himſelfe, and by letters written to the Synode diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed &amp; aboliſhed this decree. His words are thus recited, <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Decret. Diſtinct.</hi> 99. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Nullus Patriarcharum</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:177845:10"/> 
               <hi>vniuerſalitis vocabulo vnqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtatur; Quiae ſi vnus patriarcha vniuerſalis dicitur, patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charum nomen caeteris derogatur.</hi> That is to ſay, Let no Patriark hereafter vſe the word of Vniuerſalitie; for if any be called vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Patriarke, the name of Patriarke, is taken away from the reſt.</p>
            <p>But when this Patriarke of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> for all this would not ceaſe his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, then <hi>Gregorie</hi> the firſt, (whom wee commonly call <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great) more ſtrongly oppoſed himſelfe againſt his pride; and by many Epiſtles written to the Emperour <hi>Mauritius,</hi> to the Empreſſe <hi>Constantia,</hi> to the Biſhoppes of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antioche,</hi> hee calls the Title of the Vniuerſall Prieſte a newe Title, fooliſh, proud, peruerſe, wicked, and profane: to which if they did yeelde, were all one as to denie the faith.</p>
            <p>And amongſt other things, hee thus writes; <hi>Ego fidenter dico, quia quiſquis ſe vniuerſalem ſacerdotem vocat, vel in elatione</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Libro.</hi> 6. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 30</note> 
               <hi>ſua vocari deſiderat, antichriſtum praecur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> I ſpeake it bouldly, whoſoeuer calles himſelfe Vniuerſall Prieſte, or deſires in the pride of his hearte ſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177845:10"/> to bee called, is the fore-runner of Anti-Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And that this was true, the euent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward declared. For, this proud Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke by his ambition gaue occaſion to <hi>Boniface</hi> the thirde, that was Pope next but one after <hi>Gregorie,</hi> that (beeing puft vp with the like pride) he demanded, yea, and obtained of the Emperour <hi>Phocas,</hi> ſtill being imbrewed in the blood of his Maſter <hi>Mauritius,</hi> the ſupremacy ouer other Biſhoppes, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould bee called the head of all Churches, and all the Churches of the whole world, ſhould be obedient to the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> This ſame murderer <hi>Phocas,</hi> hated of all men for his crueltie, ſeemes to giue conſent to the ambition of this <hi>Boniface,</hi> to the end he might haue the Romans obedient vnto him.</p>
            <p>But how vnluckily, and vnfortunat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this happened to the Church, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the euent and profaning of the holy thinges and of all religion which then followed did declare; but alſo many ſad and ſorrowfull prodigies, terrifying the minds and harts of men, did demonſtrate: all which are recorded in ancient hiſtories.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177845:11"/> For, a burning Comet appeared, a childe was borne at <hi>Bizantium</hi> hauing foure <note place="margin">Annal. Palmer.</note> feete: another without eyes and hands, whoſe inferiour parts from the loynes downeward, were like a fiſh; bloodie ſpeares appeared all the night: God wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing thereby, that the fatall time was now at hand, wherein the Popes or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ought to follow ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall things and teach all men to lift vp their hearts and mindes vnto God, were now degenerated into four footed beaſts, and the Church (depriued of her lights and of her hands, that is to ſay, deſtitute of faithfull Seers, truſtie guides, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant watchmen) ſhould now as a fiſhe ſwimme and floate amongſt the waues of the world and vnſtable alterations of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, For, ſuch Biſhops followed, as troubled the whole world with greate warres and cruell murders, and vſurped to themſelues an authoririe or power ouer Emperours and Kings. Let the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> then by their flatterers, Ieſuites, and Seminaries, boaſt &amp; ſpread abroad the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie of their ſupremacie, which (all hiſtories being conſidered) had no being before the dayes of <hi>Boniface</hi> the thirde:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177845:11"/> neither can they bring forth any other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the ſame, but onely <hi>Phocas;</hi> then whome amongſt the Emperours, that profeſſed the name of Chriſt, none liued that was more wicked, nor more cruelly minded. I ſo ſpeake of him, becauſe to make himſelfe Emperour (as he did) he murdered <hi>Mauritius,</hi> his Lord and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour. Is then the ſupremacie of the Pope ſo newe? but newer are thoſe things whereby ſuperſtitious men doe meaſure religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in poperie; amongſt which the worſhipping of Images is chiefeſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie <note place="margin">Images.</note> one knoweth, that God in the olde Teſtament forbade Images: and Chriſt teacheth vs that the ſame was ratified in the newe Teſtament, when hee ſaith that hee came not to aboliſh the Lawe, or to <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 17 1. Io. 5. 21</note> breake the commandements of the Lawe, but to fulfill them: to whom conſenteth the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Babes keepe your ſelues from Idols.</hi> It is manifeſt in the Primitiue Church, there were no Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at all tolerated, no not ſo much as of Chriſt. <hi>Ierenaeus</hi> an auncient writer, about <note place="margin">Ire. lib. 1. cap. 24.</note> the yeare of Chriſt, 185. maketh mention of the <hi>Gnoſtickes,</hi> that they had the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of Chriſt, which they propoſed to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177845:12"/> be worſhipped with the Images of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras, Plato</hi> and other Philoſophers: but this father condemnes and reproues the ſame in them. Knowen is the action of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> Biſhoppe of <hi>Salamina</hi> in <hi>Cipres:</hi> which in an Epiſtle written to <hi>Iohn</hi> the Biſhoppe of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> being the Latin Tranſlater thereof) is thus cited; When I came (ſayth he) to a Village that was called <hi>Anablatlia,</hi> and there paſſed-by, ſeeing a candle burning, demaunding what place it was, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that it was a Church, I went in, to pray.</p>
            <p>Now, there I found hanging, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the doores of the Church, a vayle waſhed and painted, and hauing an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage as it were of Chriſt or ſome other Saint; for I doe not well remember whoſe Image it was. Therefore, when I ſawe in the Church of Chriſt, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the Authoritie of the ſcriptures, the Image of a man hanging, I cut it downe, and gaue commaundement to the keepers of the ſame place, that therewith they ſhould burie ſome poore man. And a little after in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>Precor vt iubeas preſbyteros eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:177845:12"/> 
               <hi>loci deinceps praecipere, in eccleſiae Chriſti iſtiuſmodi vela quae contra religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem noſtram veniunt, non appendi.</hi> Theſe things then doe demonſtrate and declare how the Fathers of auntient time vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the commaundement of God concerning Images, when as <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> doth affirme the Images of Chriſt to bee againſt the authoritie of the ſcriptures and enemies to Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>But, after the ſupremacie of the Popes before ſpoken of was confirmed, Images alſo crept into the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeare of Chriſt 707, by <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the firſt, for hate of the Emperour <hi>Philip.</hi> By which action grewe greate contention, in the whole Empire, and at the laſt was the occaſion, that the Greeke fell from the Latine Church: In which ſchiſme the Turkiſh Empire en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, which GOD euer from that daye hath vſed as his roddes and ſcourges to purge the filthineſſe of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie.</p>
            <p>And yet for all this, fooliſh and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious men, doe recken the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images amongſt the exerciſes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177845:13"/> of ancient and Catholicke religion, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and burdening vs with the name of noueltie, becauſe wee condemne this worſhippe, and would rid it away by the authoritie of the worde of God. But now let vs come to their Maſſe, the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter and piller of their popiſh king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: <note place="margin">Maſſe inuented and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</note> The author hereof they fayne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to be, conſtantly affirming that all the Apoſtles, but eſpecially <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iames,</hi> celebrated the Maſſe. Now how friuolous this is, euerie man may eaſily knowe, that doth but conſider the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicall hiſtory and the writings of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Chriſt inſtituted his ſupper in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of his death, in that forme <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 23.</note> and manner, that the Apoſtles after deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered it to the Church. But what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion can this myſticall ſupper haue with the Maſſe, wherein the ſacrificing Prieſt doth all alone, eates alone, drinkes alone, ſpeakes alone, behaues himſelfe like a foole in a playe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all the reſt behoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him as an idle ſpectacle? Or hath Chriſt made any mention of a ſacrifice for the quicke and the dead? in the which notwithſtanding they fixe the chiefeſt vſe of their maſſe. Chriſt inſtituted his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177845:13"/> ſupper in remembrance of his death: hee neuer commaunded to apply it to the dead; much leſſe to offer his bodie and bloud dayly for their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>The Maſſe then is a newe Inuention, the authors whereof are ſuperſtitious men that haue patcht it and pieced it vp, at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers times: which (that we may omitte o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hiſtories) we wil declare out of <hi>Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> the Popes ſecretarie. For he vpon the life of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the firſt thus writes; <hi>In ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebratione (de coena domini loquitur) manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, vt ſanctus, ſanctus, ſanctus dominus Deus Sabaoth, cantaretur.</hi> Theſe wordes were at the firſt euident and did, ſaith he, touch all things as it had beene inſtituted by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> when hee conſecrated, vſed the Lords prayer. Saint <hi>Iames</hi> the Biſhoppe of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> encreaſed theſe myſteries: <hi>Baſill</hi> encreaſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: others encreaſed them. Firſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> he ſaith, that <hi>Peter</hi> conſecrated; a newe worde, whereof in the newe Teſtament, vvhen there is any ſpeech of the Supper, the Apoſtles make no mention at all: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by it can any other thing be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, but onely the reciting of the firſt Inſtitution and words of Chriſt which he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177845:14"/> vſed when hee deliuered bread and wine to his Diſciples. Againe, the auntient fathers neuer knewe any other conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but onely that wherein common bread was made myſtical, and a ſacrament or ſigne of the bodie of Chriſt, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the vſe of it; and not that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it was turned into the ſubſtance of a fleſhly body. Secondly, hee ſayeth, that Saint <hi>Iames</hi> increaſed theſe myſteries; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but, heereby he doth intolerable wronge: firſt, to the holy man; ſecondly, to all the Apoſtles. For firſt, if Saint <hi>Iames</hi> had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any thing to the inſtitution of Chriſt, hee had beene too bolde, and alſo had ſinned againſt the Lawe of Chriſt, who had commaunded his Diſciples to teach no other thing, but that which hee had deliuered vnto them. Secondly, if the <note place="margin">Matt. 28. 20.</note> Apoſtles had ſuffered any ſuch matter, they had beene vnfaithfull in their office, and had neglected the Church; which Chriſt will haue free from burden of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane traditions. But the writinges and actions of the Apoſtles doe teach vs to iudge farre otherwiſe of them. When the Corinthians had chaunged the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Supper of CHRIST into a luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177845:14"/> or want on banquet; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies, that hee deliuered nothing vnto them, but that which hee had receiued from Chriſt: recalling them in ſuch ſort to the firſt inſtitution, that in the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thereof hee differs not one word from thoſe things that other Euangeliſtes had deliuered; &amp; pronounceth all them to be accurſed (whether they bee men or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells) <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8</note> that durſt adde anye thinge to the Goſpell alreadie preached by the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And ſhall wee then thinke, that hee would tolerate ſo filthy a profaning of the myſticall Supper, who withſtoode <note place="margin">Gal. 2 11</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> to the face, when hee (as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge the conuerſation of life) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing varied from the trueth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell?</p>
            <p>Moſt vaine therefore and fooliſh, is all that the Popes ſpeake concerning the Apoſtles, that they inſtituted or celebrated their Maſſe. But let vs returne to <hi>Platina,</hi> that the vanitie hereof may be more appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. For, when hee had ſaide that others encreaſed it, he addeth; for, <hi>Celeſtinus</hi> gaue the <hi>Introit: Gregorie</hi> the <hi>Kyrieliſon: Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macchus</hi> the <hi>Gloria in excelſis deo: Gregorie</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:177845:15"/> the third to the ſecret of the Maſſe, <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſolennitas hodie in conſpectu tuae ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtatis celebratur, domine Deus noster in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to orbe terrarum: Alleluia</hi> was taken out of the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> the Creed in the Councell of <hi>Neece: Pelagius</hi> the Commemoration of the dead: <hi>Leo</hi> the third, Frankincenſe: <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt, the kiſſing of the Pax: <hi>Sergius,</hi> the Agnus dei. <hi>Nicolas</hi> the firſt, the Sequences: <hi>Gelaſius Africanus</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Nauclerus)</hi> the Hymnes, Collects, <hi>Reſponſories, Graduals</hi> and <hi>Prefaces: Ierome,</hi> the Epiſtle and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt, <hi>Orate pro me fratres</hi> and the <hi>Deo gratias,</hi> the Cannon alſo <hi>ſanctum ſacrificium immaculatam hoſtiam, &amp;c.</hi> Now, beloued, if all theſe thinges, which <hi>Platina</hi> and others affirme to haue beene inſtituted at diuers times, and by ſundry men, were taken from the Maſſe, what I beſeech you would be therein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, that ſhould deſerue the name of a maſſe or a ſacrifice? Why then ſhould that be called an ancient faith or religion, whoſe chiefe foundation being firſt layde many yeares after Chriſtes Aſcenſion into heauen, was afterward confirmed by new rubbiſh being added vnto it?</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:177845:15"/>
            <p> But admit, that ſome of thoſe things, of the which wee haue hitherto ſpoken, being added to the inſtitution of Chriſt, are in ſome ſort tolerable; yet our aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers were altogether ignorant of the Corporall preſence of Chriſt in his Supper, and tranſſubſtantiation of bread into his body, whereupon the authoritie of the Maſſe depends.</p>
            <p>The firſt diſputation here of was in the <note place="margin">Bertram</note> yeare of grace 844. as may bee gathered out of the bookes of <hi>Bertram,</hi> which he writ at the commaundement of <hi>Carolus Calvus</hi> concerning that matter. Then <hi>Sergius</hi> the ſecond, who was the firſt that changed his name ſate in the Romiſh ſea; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sergius</hi> 2. <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </note> For, whereas before hee was Pope he was called <hi>Os porci,</hi> ſwines-mouth: hee then tooke vpon him the name of <hi>Sergius:</hi> by which action God was willing to teſtifie to the whole world, what a boare ſhould come out of the Forreſt, whom <hi>Dauid</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes <note place="margin">Pſal. 80. 13.</note> to be the deſtroyer and waſter of the Church; and that the time of defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was at hand, wherein they that by baptiſme had giuen their names vnto Chriſt, by denying him ſhould follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuperſtitions. For, ten yeares after aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177845:16"/> into that place a womaniſh harlot to be Pope, hauing to name <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight, or rather <hi>Ioane</hi> the firſt. God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting thereby, that now that harlot beganne to ſhewe her ſelfe whereof <note place="margin">Apoc. 17. 3.</note> Chriſt had prophecied in the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>But as yet they were not able to perſwade all men to worſhippe this their newe Idoll: but alwayes GOD ſent ſome to teſtifie of the truth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till in the yeare of Chriſt 1215, vnder <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thirde in the Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> there was a decree made concerning Tranſubſtantiation, which in the Decretals is thus reade; <hi>Vna eſt fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um vniuerſalis eccleſia, extra quam nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus omnino ſaluatur: in qua idem ipſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos eſt ſacrificium, Ieſus Chriſtus, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius corpus &amp; ſanguis in ſacramento alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſub ſpeciebus panis &amp; vini veraciter continentur; tranſubſtantiatis pane in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, &amp; vino in ſanguinem, poteſtate diuina: vt ad perficiendum myſterium vnitatis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiamus ipſi de ſuo, quod accepit ille de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is one vniuerſall Church of the faithfull, without which none canne
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177845:16"/> bee ſaued: wherein the Prieſt himſelfe Chriſt Ieſus is the ſacrifice, whoſe bodie and blood in the ſacrament of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar vnder the formes of bread and wine are truely contained; the bread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tranſubſtantiated into his bodie, and the wine into his bloud, by a diuine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: &amp; that the vnitie of this myſterie might be effected, wee receiue from him that which he tooke from vs.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Councell alſo was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Auricular confeſſion: whereby men of euery ſtate and degree being faſt chayned together as with fetters and linkes of Iron, durſt neuer ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the decrees of the Romiſh Church. Tenne yeares after that, <hi>Honorius</hi> the thirde, commaunded darke places, or Cheſtes to bee made, wherein the bread alreadie conſecrated (or rather as they ſpeake tranſubſtantiated into the bodie of Chriſt) was reſerued to bee worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: which without all doubt are thoſe ſecret places whereof Chriſt ſpeakes, <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 23.</note> commaunding vs not to beleeue them, who ſhewe vs Chriſt to be contayned in them.</p>
            <p>And to fulfill and finiſh all this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177845:17"/> ſuperſtition, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the fourth in honour <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vrban.</hi> 4. <hi>inuented the Feaſt of Corpus Chriſt.</hi> 1264.</note> of this ſacrament, at the requeſt of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſe (with whom, in times paſt, hee had beene ouermuch familiar) inuented the ſolemne Feaſt, which they call <hi>Corpus Chriſti.</hi> Who is it then that can affirme the whole worſhippe of the Maſſe to be auncient, ſeeing it hath not alwaies beene in the Church? neither hath it beene inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and receiued at one time; but, being brought in by little and little, was aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with newe additions dayly. So to that to the Maſſe neither leſſe nor more hath happened then to a pilgrimes ſcrippe or to an old cloake of a begger, that beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth from doore to doore: vpon ſuch a Cloake, the elder that it is, the more pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches doe they ſet vpon it; ſo that in time, nothing is ſeene, but heere a little peece, &amp; there another of the cloath whereof it was firſt made. And this clothe is ſo vſed, ſo waſted, ſo diſcoloured, and ſo without being, that it no way appeareth to be that which it was. In this cloake are not ſeene but patches of cloth corrupt and rotten, very ill placed and worſe ſowed together; ſo that it cauſeth loathing to thoſe that haue bin delicately brought vp. Such ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177845:17"/> cloake is the Popiſh Maſſe. The cloath whereof it was made, was the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord: which, men not celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting according to the inſtitution of Chriſt, waxed olde, loſt it colour, being nothing worth. Then commeth one and caſteth a peece vnto it: afterwarde, comes another and caſteth vnto it, &amp;c. So that now it is not the Supper of the Lord, but the maſſe of the Pope: now it is not the robe of an honourable man, but the cloak of a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe begger. In concluſion, their Maſſe is their <hi>Helen,</hi> for whom they trouble the whole world.</p>
            <p>What wee haue ſpoken of all the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid popiſh trumperies, the like may alſo bee ſaide of the Inuocation of Saints: <note place="margin">Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints.</note> which they can prooue by no teſtimonie nor example of the ſcripture. For, by the ſcripture wee are taught to inuocate one God, through the onely Mediator Chriſt Ieſus: neither hath any one of the Saints either of the olde or newe Teſtament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aliue, prayed vnto any of the Saints in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now the Leyturgie (which <hi>Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> makes to be twofolde: to wit, the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior</hi> &amp; the <hi>minor)</hi> is alſo confeſſed to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by men: the one by <hi>Mamertus</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177845:18"/> the raigne of <hi>Zeno,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, foure hundred foure-ſcore and ten; the other by <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, in the yeare of Chriſt fiue hundred foureſcore and tenne. The hymne of <hi>Salue regina,</hi> was made by <hi>Hermannus Contractus:</hi> and <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ninth commaunded it to bee ſung to the prayſe of the Virgin at certaine houres of the day; in the yeare of Chriſt 1241. The verie ſame may bee ſpoken of the whole worſhippe of the Saints: which how great ſoeuer it is, yet it is nothing but onely the inuention of ſuperſtitious men.</p>
            <p>But, if wee ſhould come vnto other points of their popiſh religion, as of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh orders, choyſe of meates, ſingle life of their Prieſts, fire of Purgatorie, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the dead, ſatisfactions, popiſh pardons, and multitudes of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; it would then appeare, that they were all the inuentions of man, and had their beginning when the pure doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the trueth was for the moſt part extinguiſhed, by the corruptions &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men. In concluſion then, if the lawe, which was 400 and 30 yeares after the promiſe, was not able to diſannull the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177845:18"/> couenant that was confirmed before of God in reſpect of Chriſt, to make the promiſe of none effect; much leſſe the Popes ſupremacie, the worſhipping of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, the inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saints, or any popiſh ſuperſtition whatſoeuer ſhall be able to corrupt, abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate or diſannull it, but that the promiſe ſhould bee performed to the ſeede of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> that is, to the faithfull in all ages.</p>
            <p>That then, which wee our ſelues muſt hold concerning faith onely iuſtifying, &amp; the ſole ſauiour Chriſt Ieſus, is all groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the eternall couenant of God, which in the beginning was made with our firſt parents: Secondly, renued with <hi>Abraham:</hi> Thirdly, ſet forth by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: Fourthly, confirmed and fulfilled in the death of the Sonne: And laſtly, divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the miniſtrie of the Apoſtles, through the whole world. This faith was kept by all thoſe that pleaſed and ſerued God before the comming of Chriſt in the fleſh; the martyrs ſealing the ſame with their bloud. Who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deny, but that the Papiſts doe wickedly &amp; ſhamefully ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der vs, who tax vs with nouelty, becauſe they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177845:19"/> would vnder a lying title of antiquitie thruſt vpon the common ſort their popiſh ſuperſtitions: which indeed are newe, and altogether vnknowen vnto Antiquitie.</p>
            <p>But it is more then time for vs to come to our Apoſtle: who, being about to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that which before hee had ſpoken, ſayth; for, if the enheritance be of the law, it is no more by promiſe: but God gaue the inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> by promiſe. In which words the Apoſtle oppoſeth the law &amp; the promiſe one againſt another, as things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie, and diuided, which cannot ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the cauſe and action of our Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. For, the lawe requireth workes, ſaying, <hi>Qui fecerit iſta praecepta, viuet in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lev. 18. 5</note> hee that ſhall doe theſe commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhall liue in them: but the promiſe requires that wee ſhould beleeue; neither is it apprehended by any other meanes then by faith. Therefore, as merite and grace cannot ſtand together: no more can the lawe and the promiſe. To ſette forth the ſenſe of the words, we wil frame this argument; If wee deſerue the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of life by the workes of the lawe, then it is not obtained freely, nor by faith onely. But God gaue the inheritance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177845:19"/> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> by promiſe. Therefore, this inheritance comes vnto vs not by merite, but by the free promiſe of God. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmes this argument by the word of <hi>giuing;</hi> whereby is vnderſtood a free gift: and euerie gift excludes all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of euery worke whatſoeuer on our part.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Apoſtle fitly vſeth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Abraham;</hi> becauſe hee did not ſuſtaine a priuate but a publike perſon, in whom God was willing to propoſe to the whole world an example of all that were to bee ſaued, together with an aſſured &amp; common meanes of ſaluation to all the elect. The Apoſtle handling this example in the Romanes, after the ſame ſaith thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 23. 24</note> Now it was not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for him onely, that it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe; but alſo for vs, to whom it ſhal be imputed for righteouſnes, which beleeue in him that rayſed vp Ieſus our Lord from the dead: which was the very cauſe that thoſe promiſes that were made vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> are extended vnto the ſeede of <hi>Abraham;</hi> that is, vnto all the poſteritie of Gods children. For, vnleſſe it were ſo, there would bee no profit of that ſacred and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177845:20"/> holy hiſtorie. But at this inſtant the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth thus ſtrongly vrge this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he might preſſe and beate to the ground the hautineſſe of the confidence of the Iewes: who where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they boaſted themſelues to bee the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet would they not enter into the inheritaunce promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by the faith that <hi>Abraham</hi> did: The Apoſtle therefore teacheth them, that whilſt they vrged the righteouſneſſe of the lawe, they did (as much as in them lay) fruſtrate and make voyde the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and promiſe of God, in which all their dignitie did conſiſt.</p>
            <p>As this was an errour in the Iewes, ſo is it no leſſe in the Papiſts, who would be accounted the onely worſhippers of the Saints, and the maintainers of their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For, whileſt that they enuiouſly contend againſt vs for the ſame, they doe euert and confound their doctrine, and doe very farre vary from the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of faith and life, wherein the Saints went before vs.</p>
            <p>But, if they will maintaine the cauſe of the Saints; why doe they not heare the Apoſtles? who knewe no other
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177845:20"/> thing but Ieſus Chriſt and him crucified; <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 2 Act. 4. 12</note> affirming no name to bee giuen vnto men vnder heauen, wherein wee muſt bee ſaued, but onely the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. Why doe they not obey the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <note place="margin">Ioh. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Marie,</hi> ſpeaking of CHRIST, and ſaying; Whatſoeuer hee ſayeth vnto you, doe it. Hee himſelfe commaundes <note place="margin">Mat 1. 28 Ioh. 14. 6.</note> all that doe labour and are heauie loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, to come vnto him; teſtifying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe onely to be the way whereby we muſt come vnto the Father. All this truely conſidered, then I conclude thus; that our iuſtification and ſaluation is by the Apoſtles ſo aſcribed vnto the free mercie of GOD, performed to vs-warde in Chriſt, that from thence is excluded the whole lawe, with all the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of our owne workes. But, our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries will obiect and ſay: If the lawe doe not iuſtifie, and that we muſt not hope for ſaluation by the law, why hath God giuen a lawe? Againe, if faith onely iuſtifie, and <note place="margin">Why the law was giuen.</note> that our auntient fathers were iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed and ſaued by faith, what neceſſitie was there that there ſhould be a law giuen to poſterities afterward? For, what hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was there, but that wee as well
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177845:21"/> as they might be ſaued without a lawe? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if we be now ſaued without a law, &amp; (forſaking the lawe) vpon neceſſitie muſt come vnto Chriſt; then vainely hath God giuen and deliuered a lawe afterwarde. For, thus the naturall and carnall man (if hee doe abuſe any thing, and therefore be accuſed) is alwayes accuſtomed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the ſame, and caſt it away as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hurtfull and vnprofitable. Neither doth hee make any other vſe of good and neceſſarie things, then drunken men doe of their wine. For, if thou accuſe a drunken man for the immoderate and exceſſiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of wine, hee preſently will make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere and ſay; If it be not lawfull for me to drinke, why hath God giuen wine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs? why doe wee receiue ſo plentifull a vintage from him? as if there were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſe of wine, but for their drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> The ſame doe our aduerſaries in thinges belonging to Religion. For, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue them that doe binde Chriſts cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall preſence to the ſacrament: and they will preſently make anſwere and ſay; If Chriſt be not corporally preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to what purpoſe were ſacraments giuen? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath God ſpoken after ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177845:21"/> Might hee not haue ſpoken more ſimplie, and plainely, that we ſhould haue taken his words otherwiſe; ſhall we now reproue God of a lye, or affirme him to be a deceiuer, ſuch a one as is willing to beguile with magnificall words? Againe, they doe the like, that binde ſaluation to the merite of their workes. For, accuſe them of error, preſently they will affirme, that wee altogether denie, and tread vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote good workes: becauſe they knowe no other ende nor vſe thereof, but that which they haue inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in their owne braineſicke humour. Like vnto all theſe, was the confidence of the Iewes, &amp; of ſuch as by them were deceiued in the time of the Apoſtle: from whom were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard theſe words; Hath not GOD giuen vs a lawe? Then, what is the vſe of the lawe, if faith onely iuſtifie? and if the lawe bee nothing auaileable to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherefore (as ſayeth my text) then ſerueth the lawe? Is it not altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and ſuperfluous? To this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and ſo to all the reſt that are ioyned to it, the Apoſtle in fewe words making anſwere ſaith, It was added for tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, till the ſeede came vnto the which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177845:22"/> the promiſe was made. Heere the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle expoundeth that which before he had ſpoken: Namely, that the couenant of God was not able to bee fruſtrated by the lawe that followed, 400. and 30 yeares after; for, hee ſayth that the lawe was added vnto the promiſe or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Now, that which is added vnto a thing, is added not to aboliſh it, but to confirme it. And therefore, the Apoſtle writing to the Romanes affirmeth, that the lawe entred, for this purpoſe, that <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 7</note> the fault of our ſinne, might bee appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent vnto vs; and that we, better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the horror thereof, might flee vnto the promiſe of the free mercie of God made vnto vs in Chriſt. Againe, when hee ſaieth that the lawe was added vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the promiſe, hee manifeſtly thereby teacheth vs, that in the action of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation the chiefeſt part thereof is due to the free promiſe or couenant of GOD: vnto which, the lawe was added, not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh or take it away; but to be ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto it, &amp; more to confirme it. And thus the Apoſtle doth reproue the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce of the Iewes, who did not diſtinguiſh betweene the lawe and the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177845:22"/> promiſe; and therefore attributed vnto the lawe, that which indeede was due and belonging vnto the promiſe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> Heere then obſerue, that this confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is the occaſion of all errors in the matter or cauſe of our eternall ſaluation. For, wee are all by nature ſinners, ſubiect to condemnation: but God, pitying vs, in his eternall decree appointed Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus to be our Sauiour, in whome hee hath elected vs before the world was made or created: promiſed him vnto our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: after that to <hi>Abraham</hi> and other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that thereby hee might ſhew vs, that ſaluation comes vnto men from the free mercie of God. Afterwarde, hee gaue a lawe: not becauſe the promiſe and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was defectiue or imperfect, or that hee would aboliſh the ſame; but onely to admoniſh them of their dutie, who already were heires of theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and of free ſaluation. But, as the Iewes (in times paſt) not obſeruing the order of God, ſuppoſed that this inheritance came from and by the lawe, altogether negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the promiſe: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> So in like ſort doe the Papiſtes, who doe impute ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto the merit of their owne workes;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177845:23"/> which is all one as if a ſonne ſhuld auouch himſelfe to bee his fathers heire, by the merite and deſert of Obedience, and ſhould denie himſelfe to bee an heire borne. The ſame error is committed by many in the Sacraments. The chiefeſt points of the Sacrament of Baptiſme are <note place="margin">Baptiſme.</note> theſe. The grace of Adoption, Waſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of our ſinnes, Regeneration and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation of the whole man. The duetie of the commer is this: faith is required of the baptized, and they are admoniſhed of their duetie, namely to leade and liue a life beſeeming their Chriſtian profeſſion. Now the Anabaptiſtes (a contentious and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne kinde of men) doe pauſe (nay, ſtand <note place="margin">Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</note> ſtill and ſticke) vpon this laſt point; and becauſe they ſee, that faith and the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of faith haue not as yet any place in Infants, therfore they exclude them from baptiſme: neuer obſeruing that the more principall and chiefe points take roote &amp; place in them, to wit, the grace of adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, waſhing away of ſinnes by the blood of Chriſt, Regeneration, and other things that make vs heires of eternall ſaluation. For, if they did but perceiue this, then would they conclude with the Apoſtle
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177845:23"/> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> and ſay, Can any man forbid water, but that theſe who are capable of the holy <note place="margin">Act. 10. 47</note> Ghoſt, ſhould be baptized as well as they that are well growen?</p>
            <p>The like is the error about the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Supper of Chriſt. The chiefeſt point <note place="margin">The Lords Supper.</note> therin, is the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his death. For Chriſt himſelf, when he inſtituted it, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the Apoſtle afterward commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this to be the proper ende and vſe of it. Now, vnto this is ioyned the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the bodie and blood of Chriſt with his Church, the ſealing of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; admoniſhing vs continually of our duetie, that wee ſhould not onely ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from ſtrange ſacrifices, but alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace mutuall peace and loue together: All which, that we might truely and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly performe, Chriſt (in a ſacramentall manner of ſpeech) hath called the breade his bodie; and the wine, the blood of the newe Teſtament. Now, our aduerſaries (the Papiſts) cleauing to the laſt wordes, doe contende and diſpute about the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the body of Chriſt, and corporall eating of the ſame: and thus haue they made an Inſtrument of diuiſion &amp; diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that which ſhould be the bond
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177845:24"/> of Chriſtian concord. Theſe things then doe admoniſh vs, that in euerie matter we ſhould haue a reſpect vnto that which is the chiefeſt; referring all the reſt, vnto ſuch a ſcope, that will not ſuffer vs to decline from the truth. But, let vs returne to the expoſition of our text; in the which are three things to be conſidered. Firſt, why the lawe was added to the promiſe? Secondly, how long the lawe was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue? Thirdly and laſtly, by whome and how the lawe was giuen and deliuered.</p>
            <p>As touching the firſt, the Apoſtle ſaith it was added for trangreſſions. This may bee taken two manner of waies. Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> referres it to the Fathers that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode not in the couenant; but being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with the ſuperſtitions of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and drowned in all manner of ſinnes, made themſelues like vnto the heathen, whome GOD had caſt out before their eyes; and therfore muſt be bridled, and reduced into the way by a lawe. From which, this ſentence ſeemes to take his beginning, <hi>Ex malis moribus, bonae leges natae ſunt.</hi> Now S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> he takes this to be ſpoken more generally; and ſaieth, that the lawe was added to reproue tranſgreſſions, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177845:24"/> to humble the proud &amp; confident minds of the Iewes. For, becauſe they bragged, &amp; boaſted themſelues in their natiuitie, as if from thence they had naturall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it was neceſſarie ſaith he to humble them by a lawe; applying vnto them the ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Quaecunque lex di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom, 3, 19</note> 
               <hi>ijs qui ſub lege ſunt, dicit.</hi> Whatſoeuer, the lawe ſpeakes, it ſpeakes to them that are vnder the law. Which opinion of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> comes neere vnto the minde of the Apoſtle: who teacheth vs that by the lawe we are conuicted, that we might haue our recourſe vnto Chriſt, who hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs from the curſe of the law. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in his firſt booke <note place="margin">Ambroſ. lib. 5. in Auxenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> againſt <hi>Auxentius; Iuſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fides, non lex facit: quia, non eſt per legem Iuſtitia, ſed per fidem.</hi> Faith and not the law maketh a righteous man: for, righteouſnes is not by the law, but by faith. That the lawe doth thus manifeſt our corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Apoſtle demonſtrateth: <note place="margin">Rom, 7. 7. &amp; 9. 10.</note> ſaying, I knew not ſin but by the law: &amp; a litte further; I was once aliue without the law; but when the commandement came, ſin reuiued, and I was dead. And again: the <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 20</note> lawe entred, that the offence ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound. Therefore the vſe of the lawe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177845:25"/> is to manifeſt and reproue our ſinnes, that men might be brought to the knowledge of their owne guilt. For, becauſe we flatter our ſelues in our ſinne, therefore wee will not willingly acknowledge ſinne to bee in our ſelues, but delite in our ſinne, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we feel our ſelues conuicted thereof in our conſciences.</p>
            <p>Therefore as the law doth not aboliſh the promiſe, which is the Goſpell it ſelfe: ſo the Goſpell doth not condemne the lawe or the doctrine thereof, but rather deliuers the true vſe of it. For, the lawe of it ſelf is good, &amp; holy; finally, the teacher of true righteouſnes, becauſe it bringeth vs wholy vnto God, and to our neighbor: But by our owne corruption it comes to paſſe, that wee doe not onely diſobey the lawe, but our deſires are accuſtomed to be prouoked and ſet on fire by the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the lawe. Which wickedneſſe of our nature, the Poet acknowledging hath ſaid, <hi>Nitimur in vetitum ſemper, cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſque negata.</hi> Wherefore, we are not to make this vſe of the lawe, as that by the ſame we ſhould be iuſtified and ſaued: (for <note place="margin">Auguſt. de vera innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine; Lex data eſt, vt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia quaeretur, Gratia data eſt vt lex implere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:177845:25"/> 
               <hi>vitium prudentiae carnis per legem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrandum, per gratiam ſanandum fuit.</hi> The lawe was giuen that grace might be ſought for: grace was giuen that the lawe might bee fulfilled: the law demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated our corruption, but grace tooke it away. But, in the law we muſt behold our ſelues as in a glaſſe; that being conuicted of ſinne, we ſhould flee vnto Chriſt, whom the father hath made righteouſnes for vs, and our Mediator vnto himſelfe. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">1. Cor 1. 3</note> the Apoſtle teacheth vs how long the lawe was to continue: namely, vntill the ſeede came vnto which the promiſe was made. By the ſeede properly is vnderſtood Chriſt, in whome all Nations are bleſſed. <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the lawe.</note> But in this place the Apoſtle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehends, with Chriſt, the whole body of Chriſt; that is to ſay, the Church gathered both of Iewes and Gentiles; vnto which proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this promiſe doth belong, which is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: the firſt part appertaines vnto Chriſt himſelf; to whoſe kingdom all Nations of the world were to be ſubiect, according to the ſaying of <hi>Dauid, Aſke of me, and I ſhal giue thee the heathen for thine inheritance,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>and the ends of the earth for thy poſſeſsion.</hi> The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part belongs vnto the Church,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177845:26"/> becauſe that in Chriſt all were bleſſed that out of euery Nation did come vnto it. That therefore, which the Apoſtle doth in this place obſcurely and briefly touch, hee afterward in the 23 verſe of this Chapter doth more apparently ſet downe: ſaying, that the Iewes before faith came, were kept vnder the lawe, and ſhut vp vnto that faith, which ſhould afterwarde bee reuealed. And in the Epheſians it is ſaid, <note place="margin">Ephe 2. 13. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> that the partition wall of the law is taken away from the Gentiles, that hitherto had been ſtrangers from the Common-wealth of Iſraell, and now called vnto the faith; that of Iewes and Gentiles there might be one Church of Chriſt Ieſus. For which cauſe, afterward it was called a Catholicke Church, by reaſon it was extended to the elect, of all ages and places.</p>
            <p>Now as touching the doctrine and vſe hereof, the Apoſtle doth teach vs that they doe offend and ſinne, that extend the law beyond the bound of it, &amp; now ſeeing the true ſeede Chriſt Ieſus is already come are ſtil willing to thruſt the law vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods children. For, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Qui de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cap. in Epiſto. Galat.</note> 
               <hi>ſeipſum pro peccatis noſtris, apertè &amp;c.</hi> That is, <hi>He that gaue himſelfe for our ſinnes,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:177845:26"/> 
               <hi>doth plainely ſhewe that the law did profit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: ſeeing it ſaith that Chriſt gaue himſelf that he might ſuffer for vs, that he might Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie vs whom the law made guilty: that being deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawe by the faith of Chriſt, wee ſhould bee no longer ſinners, but righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, by our ſecond birth the children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But ſome obiect againſt this and ſay, that Chriſt (whilſt hee liued vppon the earth) kept the lawe; and therfore, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the example of Chriſt, they bring in a damnable libertie of ſinne, who doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the lawe to bee abrogated. But to <note place="margin">Chriſt fulfilled the law.</note> this I aunſwere, that Chriſt indeede kept the whole lawe, becauſe hee became ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto it, when he was made man of the Virgin: and the lawe had not as yet attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his full end, which followed onely in the death of Chriſt, by whoſe merite and power the vaile of the Temple rent aſunder; that all men might knowe, that the legall worſhip was now aboliſhed. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Chriſt kept the law, not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint but willingly, not for himſelfe but for vs; that he might both free vs from the intolerable yoake &amp; burden of the law, &amp; alſo might abrogate that ſorrowful ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemnation which the lawe denounced againſt vs: becauſe ſo long as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177845:27"/> the ſame endured, bleſsing and ſaluation whereof he is the meane for vs, could take no root in vs. Nether by this is there ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any window for the libertie of ſin. For although they that are in Chriſt are to feare no more condemnation from the law, yet is there remaining a dutie of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, wherunto we muſt alwayes be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, &amp; which they onely truely &amp; hartily performe, that are endued with a true and liuely faith. Now, we come vnto the third part of this place, wherein is ſhowed, by whom &amp; how the law was giuen; of which the Apoſtle doth in ſuch ſort ſpeake, that therby we may vnderſtand, how far more excellent the Goſpell is then the law: that therby it may be manifeſt how much they are deceiued, that ſecke for righteouſneſſe and ſaluation in the law. Of this point the Apoſtle auerreth two things: firſt, that it was ordained and giuen by Angels, or as <hi>Steuen</hi> ſpeakes, by the diſpoſition and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie of Angels. And being thus giuen, vpon neceſſitie it muſt bee glorious: But, much more glorious is the Goſpel, becauſe it was preached by the onely ſon of God Chriſt Ieſus; by the which argument the Apoſtle commends the doctrine of Chriſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177845:27"/> vnto vs in the beginning of his Epiſtle to the Hebrews. Therfore as much as Chriſt <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 1. 2.</note> doth excell the Angels, ſo far doth the Goſpell excell the law. Neither is this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hinderance vnto the compariſon, That God when hee gaue the lawe did ſpeake. For in holy ſcripture ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times doth God ſpeak to men by the miniſtry of Angels.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti. </seg>
               </label> But ſome will obiect, &amp; ſay, why might not the Goſpel be preached by an Angel? but vpon neceſſitie the Son of God muſt come into the world to be the preacher of it? To this I anſwere: In the law are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned precepts with promiſes &amp; threatnings: al which might haue been propoſed by an Angel. But the Goſpel hath in it not onely precepts of faith and promiſes of eternall ſaluation, but it beſtowes life and ſaluation itſelfe vpon vs. For it is the power of God <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16</note> to ſaluation to euery one that beleeueth: It is the word of reconciliation and of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 18. Act. 10. 6.</note> life. So that truly hath the Angell ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Peter</hi> the teacher of <hi>Cornelius;</hi> He ſhall ſpeake vnto thee words wherby thou and all thy houſe ſhall be ſaued. Finally, with the Goſpel is ioyned the enheritance of ſaluation and of the kingdom of God. Now, theſe things are of ſuch ſort, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177845:28"/> they cannot be giuen vnto vs by the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte of an Angell or any other creature whatſoeuer. For, how can he make them the heires and ſonnes of God, who is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſonne nor heire himſelfe, but adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by grace? Therefore that the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Goſpel might be firme and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, it was neceſſarie to bee preached by the eternall ſonne of God. <hi>Cirillus</hi> makes <note place="margin">Cirillus.</note> an excellent difference betweene the lawe and the Goſpell. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, ſaith he, the lawe condemned the world, and ſubdued all men rightly &amp; iuſtly, to curſing: But the Sauiour freed the world; for he came not to iudge but to ſaue the world: Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> although the law graue grace to the know ledge, of the true God, recalling men from the worſhip of Idols, and teaching to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne good from euill; yet it did not effect this perfectly indeede, but onely in part. But the grace and truth of the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne doth giue vs good things, not in figures and ſhadowes, but openly &amp; manifeſtly, &amp; by his doctrin brought vs to the perfect knowledge of faith. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the law gaue vs the ſpirit of bondage to feare: But Chriſt the ſpirit of adoptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto liberty. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, the law eſtabliſhed the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177845:28"/> circumciſion of the fleſh which (as ſaith our Apoſtle) is nothing: but Chriſt brought in the circumciſion of the heart and the ſpirit by faith. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, the law baptizeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are waſhed in water: but Chriſt baptizeth with the holy Ghoſt, and with fire. Sixtly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> the law broght vs into a tabernacle, which was a figure of true things to come. But Chriſt hath brought vs into heauen, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a tabernacle, which not man but God hath created. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seuenthly, the law brought no perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good things: but the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpel bringeth full and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute bleſsing. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> And laſtly, <hi>Moſes</hi> by the law condemnes the whole world: but the Son deliuers the world fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the curſe of the law; &amp; with the multitude of his mercy heals &amp; cures the ſicknes &amp; maladie of the world. Like as <hi>Moſes</hi> brought the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell <note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but <hi>Ioſua</hi> into the Land of promiſe: ſo the law brings men vnto a ſight of their ſins: but the grace of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel hath brought vs into the kingdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And therfore ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſt. Ego</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</note> 
               <hi>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do lego Euangeliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; video ibi teſtimonia de lege, teſtimonia de Prophetis, ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſtum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidero.</hi> For, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel ſaith <hi>Theod.</hi> ſheweth the reconciliation of God: the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:177845:29"/> of the diuell: the remiſsion of ſinnes: the departure of death: reſurrection from the dead: life eternall, and the kingdome of heauen: for the ſcope and ende of the Goſpell is the ſaluation of men. So that as well by the teſtimonies of Antiquitie, as alſo by the ſcriptures, we may ſee plainely how far more glorious the Goſpell is then the lawe. The ſecond thing that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeakes concerning the lawe, is, that it was giuen in or by the hand of a Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Thus he cals <hi>Moyſes,</hi> who in the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the law was vſed as a mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and the people. For, when the people were not able to endure the voyce of God, then God was willing to make him an interpreter of the lawe: and God tendering the peoples infirmitie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Moſes</hi> vnto himſelfe, to whom he did not onely declare his law by word, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo writ downe the ſumme of the ſame in Tables of ſtone, and gaue them to <hi>Moſes</hi> to bee deliuered to the people. That this is the true ſenſe of this place appeares by the words of <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelfe which hee ſpake vnto the Iſraelites, ſaying: When ye hard the voyce out of the midſt of the darknes <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 23. 24. 25. 26. 27.</note> (for the Mountaine did burne with fire)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177845:29"/> then yee came to me all the chiefe of your Tribes and Elders and ſaid, Beholde the Lord our God hath ſhewed vs his glorie and his greatnes, and wee haue heard his voyce out of the midſt of the fire, &amp;c. And afterward, if wee heare the voice of the Lord our God any more we ſhal die. For, what fleſh was there euer that harde the voice of the liuing God out of the midſt of the fire as we haue, and liued? Goe thou therefore, and heare all that the Lord our God ſaith: &amp; declare thou vnto vs all that the Lord our God ſaith vnto thee: and we will heare it and doe it. Heere then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> the infirmitie and weakenes of man, and how far we are from God; ſeeing wee are not able to endure the maieſtie and brightnes of Angels. Neither did the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites onely endure and ſuffer this, but the like examples we finde in the parents of <hi>Samſon,</hi> in <hi>Daniell</hi> that man of deſires, in the welbeloued Diſciples of Chriſt; whom the taſte of Gods maieſty ſhining in Angels did ſo terrifie, that they fell to the ground, and wiſt not what they ſaid. This onely argument then is ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uict the papiſts, who truſt vnto the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of their free will, and the merite of their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177845:30"/> workes. But to let them paſſe, and come vnto our ſelues; we are hereby taught to embrace the goodneſſe of God, who for vs miſerable and vnworthy wretches ſo far abaſed himſelfe that he ſpeakes vnto vs by euerie manner of meanes. This good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <hi>Moſes</hi> doth worthily commend vnto vs, teaching vs to make this vſe of it: name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly diligently, and attentiuely to heare and performe thoſe things that God ſpeakes vnto vs. But how much greater then this was the readineſſe and mercie of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, who in the ende vouchſafed to ſpeake vnto vs by his onely begotten ſon, leaſt any one ſhould pretend the ignorance of his will? Being mindefull hereof, let vs ſubmit our ſelues to his will with all our hearts, alwayes remembring the ſaying of the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes; For, if the <note place="margin">Heb. 2, 2. 3, &amp; 10. 28. 29.</note> word ſpoken by Angels was ſteadfaſt, and euerie tranſgreſſion and diſobedience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a iuſt recompence of reward: how ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, which at the firſt began to bee preached by the Lord, and afterwarde was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed vnto vs by them that heard him? And againe, if hee that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> lawe dyed without mercy, vnder
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177845:30"/> two or three witneſſes; of how much ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer puniſhment ſuppoſe yee ſhall hee bee worthy, which treadeth vnder foote the ſonne of God, and counteth the blood of the new Teſtament as an vnholy thing, wherewith hee was ſanctified, and doth deſpight the ſpirite of grace. But, to the laſt part of this Text: wherein becauſe the Apoſtle had made mention of <hi>Moſes</hi> the mediator, hee now drawes an argument from the perſon or condition of a media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, wherewith hee confutes them who would be iuſtified by the lawe. A media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, is not a mediator of one; that is to ſay, hee is not a mediator betweene ſuch as are at vnitie and peace one with another: but rather hee is one with them betwixt whom he doth mediate. But our Fathers when the law was giuen, ſtood in need of a mediator, leſt they ſhould be compelled to endure thoſe greeuous and terrible voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God himſelfe proclaiming the law: of which their neede whereas before they were ignorant, then they onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode it when the lawe was to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. By this argument, the Apoſtle eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently gathers, that the lawe is not that meanes, by which we are reconciled
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177845:31"/> with God: but rather by the lawe our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate (as before hath beene decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) is made knowen vnto vs;</p>
            <p>Namely, that being ſeparated from God, we haue nothing in our ſelues, that can defend vs before Gods tribunal ſeate. For God (indeed) profeſſed himſelfe to be their God, and deliuered vnto them a law: but vnto the ſame he added ſuch conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which whereas they were impoſſible to bee performed, they did terrifie rather then comfort miſerable men. Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf did ſend them to that great Prophet Chriſt Ieſus, of whom as touching his office of mediatorſhip, hee did beare a type and figure. But now ſome will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect &amp; ſay, Had God then broken his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, <note place="margin">Deut. 18. 15.</note> that there muſt be a new reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, and therefore a mediator? But the Apoſtle maketh anſwer hereunto ſaying, But God is one: as if hee ſhould haue ſaid, God neuer hath broken his couenant; for as he is one in eſſence, ſo is hee conſtant in himſelfe, and is neuer changed. But becauſe men doe not alwayes ſtand to thoſe conditions which GOD preſcribes vnto them, he deales after another manner with them. And therefore then alſo (for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177845:31"/> matters before ſpoken of) there was a Lawe giuen, which continued for a time, ſo long as there was vſe of it: But now is the time of the new Teſtament, when the Lawe &amp; the Prophets doe yeeld vnto the Goſpell, that there might be a place as wel for the Gentiles, as the remnant of the Iews, who forceably entred into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. I knowe that others doe expound this place otherwiſe, and ſpeake much of Chriſt the Mediatour, of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God, and equality of the Sonne with the Father: but the whole Text of the words doth ſufficiently teach vs, that it is not agreeable to the purpoſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. Therfore let vs ayme at the true ſcope of the Apoſtle: which is to ſhew, that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and peace of conſcience, cannot be looked for from the Lawe; ſeeing the ancient Fathers, to whom the Lawe was giuen, were not able to endure the giuing of the ſame: much leſſe then ſhall we be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to abide it, if God ſhould be willing to iudge vs according to the rigour of it. Therefore as the Iewes ſtoode in neede of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be their Mediator: ſo we ſtand in need of Chriſt, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath made the Mediator of the new Teſtament for vs.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177845:32"/>
            <p> Let vs therefore acknowledge this ſo great a benefit: and leaſt wee ſhould make the goodnes of God vnprofitable for vs, let vs with a true and conſtant faith em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chriſt Ieſus; that he being truely v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited vnto vs may liue in vs, and that wee may lead in him a life beſeeming the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of Chriſt: applying alwayes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues that which Chriſt ſaid vnto his Apoſtles vpon the Mount <hi>Oliue,</hi> that <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 39. 40.</note> they ſhould watch and pray.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore apply our ſelues vnto that vocation whereunto God hath called vs: let vs watch againſt the deceites of the world and the diuell. Let vs continually meditate in the word of God, that is able to comfort vs and teach vs. Let vs giue place to the ſpirit, which God hath made an aduocate for vs. Let vs pray continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he will not ſuffer vs to faint vnder temptations. Finally, let all our hope bee fixed and faſtned in Chriſt Ieſus, who is the good ſhepheard, and wil ſuffer no man to take his ſheepe, which he hath redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with his blood, out of his hands. To him therfore with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be all honour and glory for euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177845:32"/>
            <p>Vnderſtand, Chriſtian Reader, that part of the matter contained in the ninetenth and twentith pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aforegoing, was (by him that copied out this Sermon, for the Preſſe) ſet downe in the Margent, without certaine direction for vs, where to bring it into the body of the Book. And conſequently, for want of a guide, we haue ſomwhat failed (as we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand ſince) of the due order obſerued by the Authour, in his originall Copy: which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Symmacchus,</hi> the <hi>Gloria in excelſis Deo: Ierome,</hi> the Epiſtle and Goſpell: <hi>Alleluia</hi> was taken out of the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> the Creed, in the Councell of <hi>Nice: Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> the Commemoration of the dead: <hi>Leo</hi> the third, Frankincenſe: <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt, the kiſsing of the <hi>Pax: Sergius,</hi> the <hi>Agnus Dei: Nicolas</hi> the firſt, the Sequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Gelaſius Africanus</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Naucle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus)</hi> the Hymnes, Collects, Reſponſories, Graduals, and Prefaces: <hi>Gregory</hi> the third, to the ſecret of the Maſſe, <hi>Quorum ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas hodie in conſpectu tuae Maiestatis cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratur, Domine Deus noster in toto orbe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Leo</hi> the firſt, &amp; ſo forward in order, as it ſtandeth in the booke.</p>
            <div type="errata">
               <head>Furthermore</head>
               <p>In the 3 page, line 27, reade 430: page. 14. line 10, reade Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blatha:</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177845:33"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:177845:33"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
